Guide to the Minnie Bruce Pratt Papers, 1870s-2005, bulk 1975-2005 RL.01046
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Minnie Bruce Pratt papers
1870s-2005, bulk 1975-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pratt, Minnie Bruce
RL.01046
94 Linear Feet
Minnie Bruce Pratt was born in Selma, Alabama in 1946 and raised in nearby Centreville. She received a bachelor's degree in English from the University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa and a doctorate in English Literature from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. An award-winning poet, Pratt has published collections of both poetry and essays. Pratt began teaching and grass roots organizing in North Carolina in the 1970s, and has continued her work as a professor and activist through 2008, the time of this writing. Pratt frequently makes speaking appearances at conferences and universities across the United States. Pratt has two sons, Ransom Weaver and Ben Weaver, from her marriage (1966-1975). As of 2008, Pratt resides with longtime partner, transgender activist and author Leslie Feinberg. The collection dates primarily between 1975 and 2005 and focuses on women's studies, sexual and gender identity, sexuality, and Pratt's fight against racism, sexism, imperialism and other forms of intolerance. A Writing Series comprises drafts, proofs, and galleys related to Pratt's major works through 2003, as well as materials related to shorter pieces by Pratt, reviews, print interviews, materials related to Pratt's editorial work, and personal journals. The series also contains materials pertaining to the outside funding from grants and speaking appearances that Pratt obtained to support herself as a writer. Major works represented are Pratt's poetry and essay collections The Sound of One Fork, We Say We Love Each Other, Crime Against Nature, Rebellion: Essays 1980-1991, S/HE, Walking Back Up Depot Street, and The Dirt She Ate. Other series in the collection are Correspondence; Family, consisting of early correspondence, mementos, photographs, and genealogical information; Activism, files of newspaper clippings, fliers, and correspondence related to Pratt's grass roots organizing; Teaching, Financial, Photographs, Audiovisual Material, Printed Material, and Ephemera. Notable correspondents include Mumia Abu-Jamal, Dorothy Allison, Judith Arcana, Elly Bulkin, Chrystos, Holly Hughes, Audre Lorde, Adrienne Rich, and Mab Segrest.
Access Restrictions
Personal journals dated September, 1991 and beyond are closed, as are all materials related to Leslie Feinberg, unless written permission from the donor is obtained. Additionally, audio interviews are restricted unless permission from the interviewee is obtained.With those exceptions, the collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Minnie Bruce Pratt Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2006 and 2007.
Biographical Note
Minnie Bruce Pratt was born in Selma, Alabama in 1946 and raised in nearby Centreville. She received a bachelor's degree in English from the University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa and a doctorate in English Literature from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. An award-winning poet, Pratt has published collections of both poetry and essays. Pratt began teaching and grass roots organizing in North Carolina in the 1970s, and has continued her work as a professor and activist through 2008, the time of this writing. Pratt frequently makes speaking appearances at conferences and universities across the United States. Pratt has two sons, Ransom Weaver and Ben Weaver, from her marriage (1966-1975). As of 2008, Pratt resides with longtime partner, transgender activist and author Leslie Feinberg. Some of Pratt's major writing and organizing accomplishments appear in the Chronology List below.
Chronology List
1977 Founded WomanWrites: A Southeastern Lesbian Writers Conference.
1978 Became member of Feminary editorial collective.
1981 Published The Sound of One Fork.
1984 Founded LIPS, a lesbian action group that organized political demonstrations on a variety of issues.
1985 Published We Say We Love Each Other.
1988 Published Yours in Struggle: Three Feminist Perspectives on Anti-Semitism and Racism with Elly Bulkin and Barbara Smith.
1989 Published Crime Against Nature.
1989 Crime Against Nature chosen as The Academy of American Poets' Lamont Poetry Selection.
1990 Creative Writing Fellowship in Poetry, National Endowment for the Arts; Crime Against Nature nominated for a Pulitzer Prize.
1991 Published Rebellion: Essays 1980-1991; Received American Library Association's Gay/Lesbian Book Award for Crime Against Nature.
1995 Published S/HE.
1999 Published Walking Back Up Depot Street; Co-founded Rainbow Flags for Mumia campaign, a national lesbian/gay/bisexual/transgender campaign to free Mumia Abu-Jabal.
2003 Published The Dirt She Ate and The Money Machine: Selected Poems.
2004 Received Lambda Literary Award in Lesbian Poetry for The Dirt She Ate.
Collection Overview
The Minnie Bruce Pratt Papers contain materials dating from the 1870s to 2005, with the bulk of the collection dating between 1975 and 2005. Materials in the collection document Pratt's work as a teacher, poet, writer, and activist. Specifically, the collection focuses on women's studies, sexual and gender identity, sexuality, and Pratt's fight against racism, sexism, imperialism and other forms of intolerance. The collection is organized into ten series: Writing, Correspondence, Family, Activism, Teaching, Financial, Photographs, Audiovisual Material, Printed Material, and Ephemera.
The Writing Series comprises drafts, proofs, and galleys related to Pratt's major works through 2003, as well as materials related to shorter pieces by Pratt, reviews, print interviews, materials related to Pratt's editorial work, and personal journals. The series also contains materials pertaining to the outside funding from grants and speaking appearances that Pratt obtained to support herself as a writer. Subseries include: Journals, The Sound of One Fork, We Say We Love Each Other, Crime Against Nature, Rebellion: Essays 1980-1991, S/HE, Walking Back Up Depot Street, The Dirt She Ate, Feminary, Workers World, Other Writings, Grant Applications, Interviews, Gigs, and Manuscripts by Others.
The Correspondence Series contains correspondence Pratt sent and received after 1966, the year of her marriage. Subseries include: Personal Correspondence, Literary Correspondence, and General Correspondence. Notable correspondents include Dorothy Allison, Judith Arcana, Elly Bulkin, Chrystos, Holly Hughes, Audre Lorde, Adrienne Rich, and Mab Segrest.
The Family Series contains materials related to Pratt's childhood and relatives, including legal and business papers, genealogical information, correspondence, mementos, and photographs. The bulk of the material dates to the twentieth century, but a few documents and several photographs date to the nineteenth century. Subseries include Brown-Carr Family, Pratt Family, Minnie Bruce Pratt, Ransom Weaver and Ben Weaver, and Leslie Feinberg.
The Activism Series documents Pratt's work as an activist supporting diversity and fighting intolerance. The series comprises newspaper clippings, fliers, correspondence, and logisitical arrangements pertaining to Pratt's organizing, conference attendances, and personal research. Subseries include: Anti-Ku Klux Klan, Fayetteville, National Endowment for the Arts, and Other Issues.
The Teaching Series documents Pratt's work as an educator at various universities, primarily The Union Institute and Hamilton College. The series comprises course syllabi, materials to supplement teaching, seminar evaluations, contracts, general faculty documents, catalogs, newspaper clippings, and correspondence. The series contains correspondence from Mumia Abu-Jamal during his application process to The Union Institute for graduate studies.
The Financial Series consists of tax returns for the years 1981 to 2004 as well as detailed narratives carefully documenting deductions taken by Pratt related to her writing and teaching career.
The Photographs Series contains photographs documenting events and individuals in Minnie Bruce Pratt's life, with descriptions provided by the donor.
The Audiovisual Material Series contains miscellaneous audiovisual material pertaining to Pratt's speaking engagements, interests, and personal life. The series includes speeches and readings given at gigs, interviews, audio correspondence, programs related to lesbian issues, and instructional materials. Materials are organized into subseries depending on format and include Audio Cassettes, Compact Discs, and Videos. Use copies will need to be created before items can be accessed by researchers. Additionally, interviews are restricted unless permission from the interviewee is obtained.
The Printed Material Series contains periodicals, booklets, printed essays, and chapbooks arranged alphabetically by title. Subjects represented include poetry, women's studies, feminism, lesbianism, and the Ku Klux Klan. A number of periodicals were removed from this collection and added to the Women's and LGBT Movements Periodicals Collection. Minnie Bruce Pratt's personal library comprising several hundred books including her own work and anthologies containing her work have been cataloged separately.
The Ephemera Series comprises miscellaneous items collected by Pratt and chiefly contains t-shirts, buttons, and posters related to Pratt's activism, the conferences and demonstrations she attended, and Feminary. Posters also document Pratt's book relases, speaking appearances, seminars, and courses. Additional items include candlesticks given to Pratt upon her marriage to Marvin Weaver, a birthday coffee mug from Leslie Feinberg, pens with printed logos, a stamp, and a vibrator, and pair of handcuffs given to Pratt by students from Iowa.
Separated Material
Minnie Bruce Pratt's personal library comprising several hundred books including her own work and anthologies containing her work have been cataloged separately. Additionally, a number of periodicals were removed from this collection and added to the Women's and LGBT Movements Periodicals Collection.
Related Material
Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jim Grimsley Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Fliers (printed matter); Pratt, Minnie Bruce -- Sound of one fork; Pratt, Minnie Bruce -- Walking back up depot street; Proofs (printed matter); Photographs; Lesbians -- United States; Politics and culture -- United States; Gender identity; Lesbian activists -- United States; Pratt, Minnie Bruce -- Rebellion; Pratt, Minnie Bruce -- S/he; Pratt, Minnie Bruce -- Crime against nature; Pratt, Minnie Bruce -- Dirt she ate; Clippings (information artifacts); Women poets, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence..; Women poets, American -- 20th century; Women authors, American -- Correspondence; Women authors, American; Women's studies; Women political activists; Racism -- United States; Pratt, Minnie Bruce -- We say we love each other; Feminism -- United States; Feminists -- United States; United States -- Race relations; Toleration -- United States; Sexuality; Sex; Rich, Adrienne Cecile; Segrest, Mab, 1949-; Pratt family; Lorde, Audre; Pratt, Minnie Bruce; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Arcana, Judith; Bulkin, Elly, 1944-; Chrystos, 1946-; Hughes, Holly, 1955 Mar.10-; Abu-Jamal, Mumia; Allison, Dorothy
- Writing Series, 1960-2005 and undated, 50 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The Writing Series comprises drafts, proofs, and galleys related to Pratt's major works through 2003, as well as materials related to shorter pieces by Pratt, reviews, print interviews, materials related to Pratt's editorial work, and personal journals. The series also contains materials pertaining to the outside funding from grants and speaking appearances that Pratt obtained to support herself as a writer. The subseries are arranged chronologically, starting with Pratt's journals, followed by her major works, and then Feminary, Workers World, Other Writings, Grant Applications, Interviews, Gigs, and Manuscripts by Others. The first subseries, Journals, contains journals filled with Pratt's daily thoughts and activities. Major works represented in the Writing Series are Pratt's poetry and essay collections The Sound of One Fork, We Say We Love Each Other, Crime Against Nature, Rebellion: Essays 1980-1991, S/HE, Walking Back Up Depot Street, and The Dirt She Ate. The Feminary and Workers World subseries document Pratt's editorial work as well as writing. Other Writings includes miscellaneous works not related to Pratt's major books. Grant Applications documents Pratt's attempts to gain funding to support herself as a writer. The Interviews subseries contains print interviews by other individuals about Pratt. The Gigs subseries pertains to Pratt's speaking and conference appearances. Manuscripts by Others comprises writings by other individuals that were sent to Pratt for her perusal or commentary. Pratt's original folder titles were retained.
  - Journals, 1960-2005 and undated, 11 boxes
    Pratt chronicled her daily thoughts and activities in journals, which are chronologically arranged within the subseries.
    - 1960 June-1963 November (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1966 January-1975 December (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1976 January-1978 May (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1978 May-1980 February (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1980 March-1981 October (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1981 October-1983 September (6 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1983 September-1986 December (6 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1986 December-1990 August (6 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1990 August-1992 November (4 folders) (Box 9)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Journals dated 1991 September and beyond are restricted.
    - 1992 November-1999 December (9 folders) (Box 10)
      All materials restricted.
    - 2000 January-2005 December (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - The Sound of One Fork, 1975-1990 and undated, 2 boxes
    Pratt self-published her first book of poetry, The Sound of One Fork, in 1981 and sold the book during her reading tour of the United States. Materials in this subseries include correspondence and drafts. The correspondence mainly consists of book orders and reviews, and is arranged chronologically. Drafts of poems are arranged alphabetically.
    - Correspondence, 1981-1990 (4 folders) (Box 12)
    - But Cato Said (Box 12)
    - Canaba (Box 12)
    - Cleaning Day (Box 12)
    - Dentata (Box 12)
    - Elbows (Box 12)
    - IWY (Box 12)
    - (Izola) (Box 12)
    - Love Poem to an Ex-husband (Box 12)
    - My Cousin Anne (Box 12)
    - My Mother Loves Women (Box 12)
    - Occoneechee Mountain (Box 12)
    - Ora: At the Carter Wedding (Box 12)
    - Rape (Box 12)
    - Romance (Box 12)
    - Sound of One Fork (Box 12)
    - Southern Gothic (Box 12)
    - The Segregated Heart (Box 12)
    - Windows (Box 12)
    - Rejected poems (Box 13)
  - We Say We Love Each Other, 1980-1992 and undated, 4 boxes
    First published in 1985, We Say We Love Each Other collects a series of what Pratt terms poetic maps as she searches for artistic and lesbian space in a difficult world. Waulking Song and the Maps poems contain some draft portions of later Walking Back Up Depot Street poems. The subseries contains correspondence, drafts, and proofs arranged chronologically. Correspondence pertains to reviews, publicity, and the book's publishers, both original publisher Spinsters Ink/Aunt Lute Press and Firebrand Books, who reissued the book in 1992.
    - Correspondence, 1984-1992 (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Waulking song (Box 13)
    - Maps 1 (Box 13)
    - Maps 2 (Box 13)
    - Maps 2A (Box 13)
    - Maps 3 (Box 13)
    - Untitled (Box 13)
    - Maps 4 (Box 13)
    - Waulking #1, 1980 (Box 14)
    - Gorgons, 1980-1984 (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Maps 2, 1981-1984 (folders 1-7 of 9) (Box 14)
    - Maps 2, 1981-1984 (folders 8-9 of 9) (Box 15)
    - Maps 3, 1982-1983 (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Final drafts, 1981 July-1985 April (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Poem drafts, 1983-1984 (Box 15)
    - Poem drafts, 1988 February-December (folder 1 of 5) (Box 15)
    - Poem drafts, 1988 February-December (folders 2-5 of 5) (Box 16)
    - Reading Maps: Three proofs, undated (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Crime Against Nature, 1988-1989, 1 boxes
    Crime Against Nature collects poetry Pratt wrote about her experiences as a feminist, lesbian mother who lost custody of her children due to her sexual identity. The Academy of American Poets honored the book as the 1989 Lamont Poetry Selection and the American Library Association awarded Crime Against Nature the Gay/Lesbian Book Award in 1991. The subseries comprises drafts, proofs, and manuscripts and is arranged chronologically.
    - Drafts, 1988 July-August (Box 16)
    - First set of corrections, 1988 September (Box 16)
    - Comments and first draft corrections, 1988 November (Box 16)
    - Manuscript as sent to Nancy Bereano, 1988 November (Box 16)
    - Last manuscript changes, 1989 November (Box 16)
    - Comments on 1988 September draft, 1989 March (Box 16)
    - Final galley proofs, corrected, 1989 December (Box 16)
  - Rebellion: Essays 1980-1991, 1975-1991 and undated, 3 boxes
    In Rebellion, Pratt connects the personal and the political in a series of autobiographical essays that detail her route to activism. Materials in the subseries are arranged chronologically, and include drafts, proofs, correspondence, and grant information.
    - I Am Born: Excerpts from a Journal, 1975 (Box 17)
    - Letter to Chrysalis, 1979 December (Box 17)
    - White Women and White Terror: Taking Down the Walls, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Who Am I If Not My Father's Daughter, 1983 August-October (Box 17)
    - Identity: Skin Blood Heart galley proofs with corrections, 1984 (Box 17)
    - LIPS Herstory Project, Civil Disobedience at the Supreme Court, 1987 (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - I Plead Guilty to Being a Lesbian, edited drafts, 1987 October (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - The Friends of My Secret Self: A Southern Lesbian Look at Class and Race, 1988 May-1990 June (Box 17)
    - My Mother's Question, copyedited drafts and published article, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Books in the Closet, in the Attic, Boxes, Secrets, 1989 (Box 17)
    - Money and the Shape of Things, 1989 (Box 18)
    - National Endowment for the Arts, writing grants, 1989-1991 (Box 18)
    - Rebellion and notes, 1990 January-March (Box 18)
    - My Dark Saying, 1991 (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Reader mail, 1991 (Box 18)
    - The Maps in My Bible, Bridges: A Journal for Jewish Feminists and Our Friends, Spring 1991 (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Poetry in Time of War, 1991 July-August (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Rebellion, edited proof, undated (Box 19)
    - Rebellion, unedited proof, undated (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Rebellion, edited proof, undated (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Rebellion, edited drafts of essays, undated (3 folders) (Box 19)
  - S/HE, 1993-2004 and undated, 3 boxes
    Pratt explores beyond the boundaries of sex, gender, and sexuality in S/HE, first published in 1995. The book was a finalist for both the American Library Association's Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual Book Award and the Firecracker Award in Non-Fiction. The subseries is composed primarily of drafts, but also includes notes and information on the book's publicity. Pratt's original folder titles were retained and files are arranged alphabetically.
    - Butch/femme, undated (Box 20)
    - Draft, 1994 December (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Essay, 1993-1994 (Box 20)
    - Galleys, undated (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Galleys, 1995 February (Box 20)
    - Gender notes, 1993-1994 (Box 20)
    - Publication party, 1995 (Box 21)
    - Publicity, 1995 (Box 21)
    - Reprint, 2002-2004 (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Revised draft, undated (4 folders) (Box 21)
    - Rights, 2001-2002 (Box 22)
    - Section One: Early years (Box 22)
    - Section Two: Early lesbian (Box 22)
    - Section Three: Meeting me (Box 22)
    - Section Four: Sex/fucking (Box 22)
    - Section Five: Femme (Box 22)
    - Section Six: Transgender/family/culture (Box 22)
    - Section Seven: Ending (Box 22)
  - Walking Back Up Depot Street, 1979-1999 and undated, 6 boxes
    Pratt's fourth collection of poetry tells the story of Beatrice, a Southern woman who seeks to uncover the truth obscured by the myths of the segregated South. The subseries primarily contains drafts and proofs arranged chronologically.
    - Second Sight, 1979-1998 July (Box 22)
    - Walking Back Up Depot Street/Red String, 1980 October-1997 December (Box 22)
    - Con Artist, 1980 December 20 (Box 22)
    - Closed Universe, 1980 November-1982 November (Box 22)
    - The Blue Cup, 1980 November-1994 (Box 22)
    - Central Prison, 1981 (Box 22)
    - What the Cat Knew, 1981 March-1994 (Box 22)
    - Cat's Eye, 1981 March 11 (Box 23)
    - Creatures, 1981 April (Box 23)
    - Walking Back Up Depot Street, miscellaneous critiques, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
    - Bust of Martha Mitchell to Be Unveiled, 1981-1983 (Box 23)
    - Walking Back Up Depot Street, Elly Bulkin's critiques, 1981-1983 (Box 23)
    - Walking Back Up Depot Street, early drafts, 1981-1983 (Box 23)
    - Shades, 1981 September-1997 December 22 (Box 23)
    - Stars, 1982 September (Box 23)
    - Strange Flesh, 1982 February-1983 March (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - The White Star, 1982-1997 March (Box 23)
    - Painting Her Fingernails Red, 1982 February-1997 September (Box 23)
    - Monthly Reminder, 1982 (Box 23)
    - The Art of Change, 1982 July (Box 23)
    - Nothing But Her Voice, 1982 September (Box 23)
    - Swingblade, 1982 September-1997 March (Box 23)
    - Vacant Lots/The Possum Eats Out of the Graveyard, 1982 October-1983 March (Box 24)
    - Button, 1982 October-1997 December (Box 24)
    - Blue Moon, 1983 February (Box 24)
    - Walking Back Up Depot Street, Elizabeth Knowlton critique, 1983 February (Box 24)
    - Occultation of Venus in the Moon, 1988 June-1997 January (Box 24)
    - The Subway Entrance, 1988 August-1997 December (Box 24)
    - The Road to Selma, 1988 November-1997 March (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - Eating Clay, 1989 March-1997 December (Box 24)
    - Erotica, 1989 August-1990 January (Box 24)
    - The Other Side, 1992 (Box 24)
    - At Deep Midnight, 1992 September-1994 March (Box 24)
    - On the Silver Coast, 1992 October-1997 December (Box 24)
    - Walking Back Up Depot Street, Adrienne Rich's critiques, 1993-1994 (Box 24)
    - The Ferry, 1993 January-1996 (Box 24)
    - Bust of Martha Mitchell to Be Unveiled, 1993-1998 (Box 24)
    - Walking Back Up Depot Street, Judith Arcana's critiques, 1993-1998 (Box 25)
    - Bone Day, 1994 January-1997 September (Box 25)
    - A Cold That Is Not the Opposite of Life, 1996 December (Box 25)
    - Central Prison/Pokeweed, 1996 December-1998 (Box 25)
    - The A and P, 1994 May-1997 March (Box 25)
    - Trash, 1996 February-1997 March (Box 25)
    - Strange Flesh, 1996 December-1997 March (Box 25)
    - Nightmare About a Black Man/The Possum Eats Out of the Graveyard, 1997 (Box 25)
    - The Petrified Woman/The Tattooed Man, 1997 January-February (Box 25)
    - Snake Eyes, 1997 February-August (Box 25)
    - The Great Migration, 1997 June (Box 25)
    - Fighting Fire, 1997 April-September (Box 25)